moving on to chapter 3 the high road to
octave inference and so recall that the
high road is like the Y
so Ali please begin just go as long as
you want on through the high road to
octave inference
okay so the high road to active
inference uh begin with uh the question
um
about about the conditions for the
Persistence of quote-unquote things I
mean uh what would we expect for a thing
to behave if it persists through time
and that's why sometimes fap is referred
to as the theory of every space thing
and it's not absolutely everything but
think just in this sense of uh I mean
persisting through time and uh the
notion that allows for this
a thing to
act as it as it persists through time is
uh markup blankets so markup blanket is
one of the most uh essential ingredients
of the high road approach to active
inference and that's why this section
opens up with
um
describing how Market blanket allows to
describe the situation of Interest
through this conceptual and mathematical
tool but one thing that I always point
out in almost all our all our textbook
cohorts is
in this section
it doesn't
um I mean
exactly describe a markup blankets
rigorously enough in terms of it's
carving up the
um I mean State space and so on so one
thing I I've
I think is can be uh clarifying in
following uh all the discussions around
Marco blanket is to keep in mind that
it's just a boundary in the state space
so it's not necessarily spatial temporal
boundary
although in many cases it manifests
itself as spatial temporal boundaries
such as the I don't know cell membranes
or organelle organelle membranes and so
on but it's not necessarily the case so
I think it it can be helpful to keep
that in mind when we every everywhere we
see markup blanket
uh but uh
in a very very simply markup blanket uh
is what allows for the agent or the
system to be statistically separated
from its environment as is shown here uh
in figure 3.1 so basically markup
blankets mathematically is just uh the
uh I mean the sensory and active States
together it consists of both of those
States
and it is statistically separates what
happened externally or internally from
each other so in other words internal
States cannot observe or infer anything
about the external States directly but
only through the markov's Markov blanket
and that's why it's essential to uh
describe the systems in this way because
obviously in any sparse coupled systems
there isn't a possibility to observe the
external States directly but only
through those sensory and active states
and and one other thing that I also
believe can be a bit confusing in this
picture is that yes typo
in the active Estates and sensory States
because it's important to observe that
active state only or the flow in the
active States more precisely
only depends on internal and Market
States or blanket States and on the
other hand in sensory sensory states
only depend on
the external and blanket States so mu
and X in those two equations should be
exchanged uh yes yeah
let me just unpack into this before we
continue to add before we continue
yes so this is what's known as the
particular partition and that
terminology was brought to the fore by
Carl friston's famous monograph in 2019
and it's a little bit of a pun it's a
particular partition because this is
just one way to partition agent from
environment figure from ground
and we call what it partitions out the
blankets and internal States as the
particle so we can think about the most
inert least cognitive particle is like a
speck of dust doing Brownian diffusion
but also there are more sophisticated
kinds of cognitive particles that can
include
World models counterfactuals what would
happen if I did this all of those kinds
of sophisticated cognitive operations
that we can explore in active inference
so note the small typo that Ali
mentioned internal States and also these
edges reflect causal possibilities
amongst internal external and blanket
States blanket constituting the active U
and sensory y States
so these are map not territory this is
not a spatial temporal
articulation these are like causal maps
of the world that may have to do with
spatial temporal boundaries but are not
simply that
and sensory data or sensory States flow
onto internal States internal states are
involved in action selection resulting
in active states which have some causal
consequence in the world the generative
process the external states which
results in different sensory States
coming in again and so the Markov
blanket is what makes the internal and
the external States conditionally
independent and that can be thought of
as just a no telekinesis no telepathy
Clause the only way that information
comes across internal and external
states which are symmetrical with each
other is through the boundary or the
holographic screen or the Markov blanket
you can continue on Ali
uh okay so
the next section is
about surprise minimization and
self-evidency so again this term
self-evidencing is a common term an
active inference literature first
proposed by Jacob Howie so uh basically
it refers to how a system or agent or in
other words a particular State can
gather the evidence for itself
persistence or self-existence through
time in other words
by inferring the state of the
environment
and comparing
that inference with its internal States
or in other words with its generative
model
it it's basically a way I mean an
interpretation of that
um that kind of inference is uh on the
on the one hand there is this dynamical
interaction between the internal and
external state but we can somehow
interpret that uh physical Dynamics as
engaging in the active in the active
inference or as a model for
um the Persistence of the agent uh
through time so that's basically what
refers to as self-evidencing and
then we go through the subsection 3.3.1
which is which sets the stage for the
recent formulation of active inference
uh as in mechanics which is to uh
somehow to to interpret the the active
surprise minimization
as minimizing the action through the
hamiltonian principle of least action
which is a variational principle uh and
by variational principle is what what is
meant here is just a computational or
mathematical tool that allows for the
computation or the derivative the I mean
specific derivations to happen so it's
not
uh identical to scientific theories or
scientific I don't know facts or
observations it's just a tool a
principle a mathematical Tool uh so
again
one of the main
misconceptions about free energy
principle is that it is on falsifiable
uh obviously if we see it in this way uh
it doesn't make sense to say that a
mathematical tool or principle is
unfalsifiable because it doesn't say
anything about the empirical evidence of
the phenomena we're talking about so
that's why here it's important to
understand how the surprise minimization
can be seen as this kind of variational
principle
and then
equation equation 3.1
draws the parallel between
the surprisal as defined in section in
chapter two sorry and this chapter so it
kind of ties up all the arguments
provided in the previous chapter with
this one and how everything comes
together in a single
formulation of active inference that but
they're just the two distinct approaches
to arrive at same destination
uh
uh and then we go uh also sorry the
other important
equation and again another key equation
here is equation 3.2
which is
a kind of EX sorry
yes equation I meant to say equation 3.2
not equation 3.1 sorry my bad so yes
the other section is about
the relations between inference
cognition and stochastic Dynamics as
uh I mean all the previous discussions
around uh how the active inference can
be seen as a kind of self-evidencing
through the variational
principles such as fep comes together to
do to
reframe the previous discussions we saw
in Chapter 2 about perception as
inference and action as inference and
to see the concepts of variational free
energy and expected free energy through
the lens of variational free energy
variational
principle of least action so uh it
unifies nicely all the material from uh
chapters two and three into
uh something that I mean not necessarily
distinct from each other but just two
sides of
awesome yeah I find table three one to
be very exciting
it draws together statistical physics
Bayesian information information Theory
and cognitive interpretations so it's
kind of like learn one thing learn many
things
statistical physics has been talking
about minimization of variational free
energy for a long time and such methods
are absolutely everyday and
professionalized in Bayesian statistics
active inference is using exactly just
that to describe perception and action
and so on so that's very exciting
box 3.2 describes
free energy in statistical physics and
active inference I sometimes joke that
we have a few kinds of free energy we
have Tesla like electrical power should
be available to everybody for no cost
we're not talking about that right now
there's Gibbs free energy which is the
quantity that makes chemical or
thermochemical reactions irreversible
like the hydrolysis of ATP and when
we're talking about variational free
energy we're talking about an
information geometric space with similar
Dynamics similar kinetics and
thermodynamics but rather than
describing the reaction coordinates of a
chemical reaction we're thinking about
it in terms of Bayesian updating and
this is all called the Bayesian
mechanics
um 3.41 continues on with variational
free energy
3.42
goes into expected free energy so we see
this A Lot F
variational free energy that's the
real-time unfolding sensory flow and
then G expected free energy and the
policy planning as inference
section 3.5 concludes with a novel
Foundation Act of inference to
understand behavior and cognition
and it describes a few features of
active inference including its
distinguishing features from a few other
ways that people have looked at behavior
in cybernetics
section 3.6 goes into a bit more detail
on models policies and trajectories
having to do with agency and policy
selection
3.7 reconciliation of inactive
cybernetic and predictive theories under
active inference again the exact kind of
thing that there's a whole literature on
and it's always amazing to hear
everybody's perspective on in the
textbook groups
3 8 active inference from the emergence
of life to agency and three nine summary
you want to just give any other thoughts
that you have on chapter three
again it's one of the uh probably most
fundamental chapters and
I mean the topics covered in this
chapter is essential
are absolutely essential to understand
everything active in Prince related but
specifically the
discussions in section
3.7 3.6 onward and again I believe uh is
really important to understand the the
broader context
of active inference and how it relates
to uh all the other theories but
specifically
section 3.8
provides a nice
um view of how we can
use the same modeling to the same
theoretical tools to model both
non-living dynamical systems or sparse
couple dynamical stochastic systems and
also to uh
the systems that as agency or sentience
so it's a much broader theoretical
framework that doesn't restrict itself
to only particular kinds of systems or
agents
and we'll see much more elaboration on
that in the later
wonderful
all right that concludes our overview on
chapter three